<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian and modest offer of a most indifferent conference, or disputation, about the maine and principall controversies betwixt the prelats, and the late silenced and deprived ministers in England tendered by some of the said ministers to the archbishops, and bishops, and all their adherents.</title>
            <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855961</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855961</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04208)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1145:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian and modest offer of a most indifferent conference, or disputation, about the maine and principall controversies betwixt the prelats, and the late silenced and deprived ministers in England tendered by some of the said ministers to the archbishops, and bishops, and all their adherents.</title>
                  <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by William Jones' secret press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Henry Jacob.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Controversial literature --  Puritan authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21472:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CHRISTIAN AND MODEST OFFER OF A MOST INDIFFERENT CONFE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RENCE, OR DISPVTATION, ABOVT the maine and principall Controverſies betwixt the Prelats, and the late ſilenced and deprived Miniſters in England: TENDERED BY SOME OF THE SAID MINISTERS TO THE Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, and all their adherents.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Theſſ. 5.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Trie all things, and keepe that which is good.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ioh. 7.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Iudge not according to the appearance; but iudge righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgment.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ioh. 18.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If I have evill ſpoken, beare witnes of the evill: but if I haue well ſpoken, why ſmiteſt thou me?</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21472:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21472:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE, <hi>IAMES, BY THE GRACE OF GOD; KING</hi> of great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defender <hi>of the faith &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MOſt High and mightie Soveraigne, As it is the office of every Chriſtian to endevour, by all good &amp; lawfull meanes, to procure the peace and proſperitie of <hi>Sion;</hi> ſo is it principally required of the Miniſters of the Gospell of Ieſus Chriſt, not onely that they be Gods <hi>Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brancers,</hi> giving him no reſt, untill he ſet up <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the prayſe of the world, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that they be humble ſuiters unto thoſe that, under him, be in ſupreme &amp; ſoveraigne Authority, that, according to their places, they will become <hi>nurſing Fathers, &amp; nurſing Mothers</hi> to the Churches of God within their Dominions. And as this is a duety that lyeth both upon Miniſter &amp; people at all times (for the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect whereof they ſhalbe accountable to that great and mightie God, whoſe ſervants they are) ſo are they then eſpecially to be carefull of it, when they ſee the truth of God, and the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt Ieſus, the ſole King and Prophet of his Church, to be oppoſed &amp; oppugned, and the ſyncere Profeſſors of the Goſpell maligned and traduced, yea oppreſſed, and in a ſort troden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foote, by men who ſeeke nothing but themſelues, and who, for the maintayning of their owne Pompe, and for the feeding of their idle bellies, ſtick not to wreſt the <hi>Scepter</hi> out of the handes of Chriſt, and to thruſt him out of his chaire of <hi>Eſtate.</hi> The conſideration hereof (moſt deare and dread Soveraigne) hath imboldened vs, Gods moſt unworthy ſervants, your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties loving and loyall Subiectes, at this time to caſt downe our
<pb facs="tcp:21472:3"/>ſelues at your royall feete, and to craue your Princely favour.</p>
            <p>Your Maieſtie knoweth right well what Controverſies there haue been amongſt us in this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, about the <hi>Prelacy, Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, &amp; Subſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ever ſince the bright ſhini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g beames of the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt firſt diſpelled &amp; chaſed away the fog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie miſtes, &amp; black darknes of Popery from out of our coaſtes. You know likwiſe how hotely &amp; egarly the Approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe things hath been vrged by the Prelates; who, being wiſe in their genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, haue left no ſtone vnrolled for the upholding of their rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous &amp; tottering kingdome; they having from time to time not onely <hi>reviled</hi> and <hi>diſgraced,</hi> both in <hi>Pulpit</hi> and in <hi>Print,</hi> thoſe whom they call their brethren, and fellow ſervants of Ieſus Chriſt (who out of a fervent Zeale of the glorie of God, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect deteſtation of Poperie, haue witneſſed againſt theſe Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) but having alſo <hi>ſuſpended, deprived, degraded,</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned</hi> them, yea cauſed <hi>them to be turned out of houſe and home, denyed them all benefit of law,</hi> and uſed them with ſuch <hi>contempt</hi> &amp; <hi>contumely,</hi> as if they were not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to liue upon the face of the earth. Shall theſe Controverſies be kept a-foote for ever? Shall they not once be finally decided &amp; determined? Will it not be miſery in the latter end, if the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates be not reſtrained in time? It is true that bookes haue been, and are daily written, on both ſides: and yet the differences are as great, and greater now, then they were at the firſt; and ſo are like ſtill to be, unles (by ſpeciall order from your Maieſtie) the matter may once come to ſome ſuch direct, and iuſt <hi>Triall</hi> as is heere offered.</p>
            <p>Wherein that your Maieſtie may be the more willing and readie to harken unto us, we beſeech you to conſider, and that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, that the Cauſe, which here we preſent unto you, is not our owne, but that it is the Cauſe of Chriſt Ieſus, who is become a <hi>Suiter</hi> vnto you, and deſireth that he may haue <hi>Audience:</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:21472:3"/>whom whatſoever you ſhall doe, it ſhalbe remembred unto you, and abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly recompenſed at that great &amp; laſt day of account, when you ſhall come to ſtand before his <hi>Tribunall,</hi> who is King of Kinges, and Lord of Lords; who is not unrighteous that he ſhould forget any thing that is done for him, or for any cauſe of his. And howſoever the Prelates, and their followers, do beare your Maieſtie in hand, that the Church-Government deſired is an enemy to your Crowne and dignitie; beleeue them not, we hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech you, neither harken to their <hi>Syren ſonges:</hi> It is (as we are readie to proue) a holy Ordinance of God, which will ſtand when all ſuch as oppoſe it, and blaſpheme it in the eares of your Royall Maieſtie, ſhall melt away as ſnow before the Sunne. And if by ſuch an indifferent <hi>Conference</hi> as is heere tendered, we ſhall not make it as cleere unto your Maieſtie as the Sunne at Noone-day, that the Governement of the Churches of Chriſt by <hi>Paſtors, Teachers,</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> is much more agreeable to the State of a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> then is the preſent Governement by <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons, Commiſſaries,</hi> and the reſt of that <hi>Romiſh Hierarchy,</hi> let us then finde no favor in your Maieſties eyes.</p>
            <p>Your Maieſtie profeſſed before you came to the Crowne, that you did <hi>equally loue &amp; honor the learned &amp; graue men of either of theſe opinions:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Basil. dor. Epiſt. pag 11.</note> and it is no ſmall heartes-griefe unto us, that, ſince your comming into this land, your Affections are ſo alienated &amp; eſtranged from us, who haue done you no hurt in the world, but haue wiſhed you all the good that your owne ſoule deſireth; nay, who, before we ſaw your face, laboured by all good meanes (not without ſome danger) to promote your Maieſties iuſt Title to this Crowne, and haue ever ſince caryed our ſelues duetifully towards your Maieſtie, and peaceably in the ſervice of God, and of his Churches. We are not ignorant what the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates doe pretend, and what they ſuggeſt continually in your
<pb facs="tcp:21472:4"/>Princely eares; they cry out againſt us with open mouth, that we are ſtubberne and refractarie perſons, and enemies to your Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Authoritie: wherein they doe both highly abuſe your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and wrong us exceedingly. For it is well knowne, and the Lord beareth us witnes, that we doe, in the ſinglenes and ſynce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of our heartes, aſcribe much more unto your Maieſtie and the Civill authoritie under you, then any Prelate in the land ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth, or is willing to doe. And for the matters in queſtion, we profeſſe heere in the preſence of that great God, before whom we ſhall one day appeare to anſwer it, if we ſpeake not the truth, that we ſtand not againſt them out of any wilfulnes, or peeviſhnes, but out of the <hi>tendernes of our Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences,</hi> as being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our very ſoules, that we cannot yeeld unto them, without ſinning againſt Chriſt Ieſus, whoſe Miniſters and Meſſengers we are. And if, upon ſuch a due <hi>Triall</hi> of our cauſe as is deſired, the truth of the enſuing Propoſitions (which are the ſpeciall groundes on which we ſtand) ſhalbe infringed by the Prelates; nay, if we ſhall not be able to make them ſo cleere and manifeſt by the infallible &amp; undeniable evidence of the holy word of God, that who ſo doth not wilfully hoodwinke himſelfe may plainely ſee and diſcerne the truth of them; we doe heere promiſe, and binde our ſelues in the word of Chriſtians, that we will preſently change our mindes, and become wholly Conformable to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State.</p>
            <p>Wherefore we, being herein privy to our owne uprightnes both to God &amp; to our Soveraigne, cannot but conceiue ſome hope, notwithſtanding all the contrary plottes and practiſes of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, that your Maieſtie (who are even as an <hi>Angell of God</hi> to diſcerne betweene good and evill) wilbe pleaſed now at laſt both to take a more exact knowledge of our cauſe, and (out of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bowells of your compaſsion) to thinke upon and pity the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed eſtate not onely of us the Lordes poore ſervants, who are
<pb facs="tcp:21472:4"/>without any iuſt cauſe caſt out from ſerving at his <hi>Altar,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Churches of Chriſt in this land, which doe mourne and grone under the burden of humane <hi>Traditions.</hi> Oh that this ſhould be told at <hi>Gath,</hi> or publiſhed in the ſtreetes of <hi>Aſhkelon,</hi> amongſt the daughters of the uncircumciſed, that, under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of ſo worthily renowned and famous a Prince, the Churches of God haue been thus miſerably waſted, and ſuch a woful havock made in them by <hi>vſurping &amp; time-ſerving Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,</hi> as the like hath never been heard of in this land, under the Goſpell. Oh that this ſhould be either ſaid, or written in ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages, that in the raigne of Noble King <hi>Iames</hi> (whoſe name ſhall liue amongſt men, when he, having finiſhed his courſe, ſhall ſleepe with his Fathers) ſo many painefull Preachers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell (even three hundred, or there-aboutes) haue in one yeere and a litle more, been turned out of Chriſts ſervice, onely for refuſing ſuch Ceremonies, as haue their life, breath, and being from Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſuch a Subſcription, as the like, for ought we know, hath neuer been urged upon any Church of Chriſt, in any age, under a Chriſtian Magiſtrate: there being in the meane time whole ſwarmes of idle, Idole, ſcandalous, Popiſh, and Non-reſident Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters tolerated every where amongſt us.</p>
            <p>The Prelates haue left no meanes of rigour and extremitie vnaſſayed, for the ſuppreſsing of this cauſe, and for the diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging and daunting of all thoſe that either ſpeake or write for it; and yet the glorious evidence of the truth is ſuch, that it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth no <hi>witneſſes;</hi> there being at this day many hundreds of the moſt painefull &amp; profitable Preachers in this Kingdome (beſides thoſe alreadie turned out) which are readie to loſe both their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery &amp; their Maintenance, and to expoſe themſelues &amp; theirs to all manner of miſery, rather then they will renounce this Cauſe, and conforme themſelues to the Corruptions of the times. If therefore there be in the Prelates any loue of the truth, or any
<pb facs="tcp:21472:5"/>ſparke of deſire of the peace and proſperitie of our Churches (which is the thing that they ſo much pretend unto your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie) it will now appeare and ſhew it ſelf, and you ſhall eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne it, by their indeavour to procure the admittance of this <hi>Offer,</hi> which is the likelieſt &amp; the readieſt way, that hitherto hath been thought upon, both to finde out the truth, and to put a perpetuall end to all theſe long-continued Controverſies. Some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges there be, which we would willingly haue brought to this, or the like <hi>Triall,</hi> as namely, the <hi>Oth ex officio,</hi> which is a cruell a racking of the minde, as the moſt exquiſite Torture can be of the body; and ſundrie of the late <hi>Canons.</hi> But becauſe they be of another nature, and we take them to be not onely contrary to the word of God, but alſo directly againſt the lawes of the land, we mention them not in our Propoſitions, in which we haue endevoured to ſet downe onely the groundes of all the maine differences betwixt us &amp; the Prelats: which if they be once throughly debated, &amp; ſoundly agreed upon, your Maieſtie ſhall ſee ſuch a bleſſed vnitie and vniformitie in all the Churches within your Dominions, as your owne heart deſireth.</p>
            <p>May it therfore pleaſe your moſt excellent Maieſtie to reade, &amp; examine this <hi>Offer,</hi> &amp; to weigh in all the partes therof the equi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie &amp; iuſtice of it, &amp; the moſt certaine advantage that the truth (on which ſide ſoever it is) ſhall receiue by the acceptance of it: may it pleaſe you likewiſe to urge the Prelates, whom it deepely concerneth, to admitt of it; and to ſecure by Royall protection thoſe that ſhalbe <hi>Actors</hi> in it: who, howſoever they are forced to conceale their names (in regard of the rigor and ſeveritie of the Prelates) will notwithſtanding be moſt willing &amp; readie to ſhew themſelues, if your Maieſtie ſhall vouchſafe, to ſignifie your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious pleaſure touching the admittance of this <hi>Conference.</hi> If therefore we haue found favour in your Maieſties eyes, and
<pb facs="tcp:21472:5"/>if this great cauſe of Chriſts be regarded; Our humble ſuite vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Highnes is, that you would make it knowne by ſome <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Act,</hi> that the <hi>Offer</hi> ſhalbe accepted, and they protected by your Royall Authority, that haue, or ſhall haue to doe in it. So ſhall we haue occaſion, every day more and more, to intreat the Lord, as we haue done and will doe for ever, that he will conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vpon your Maieſtie, with a happy increaſe, all his graces both bodily and ſpirituall, even untill, and in the day of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Lord Ieſus bleſſe your Maieſtie, and your Royall poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and graunt vnto you a long and a happie raigne over us: the Lord multiplie all his mercyes upon you both for this and a better life, and cover with ſhame the faces of all ſuch as wiſh you the leaſt evill. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſties obedient Subjects, moſt readie to doe your will in all thinges, wherein they ſhall not diſobey the will of God:</hi> Some of the late ſilenced and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Miniſters.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21472:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21472:6"/>
            <head>A CHRISTIAN AND MODEST OFFER <hi>OF A MOST INDIFFERENT CONFERENCE</hi> or diſputation, about the maine and principall Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies betwixt the Prelats, and the late ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nced and <hi>deprived Miniſters in England:</hi> TENDERED BY SOME OF THE SAID MINISTERS TO THE <hi>Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, and all their adherents.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Wherein are ſet downe,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The Propoſitions which the Miniſters offer to maintaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prelats.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The Conditions, forme, and maner of the Conference or Diſputation.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Iuſt Conſiderations moving the Miniſters to make this Offer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>An Anſwer to ſuch oppoſiſions, as may be made by the Prelats againſt yeeiding to the ſaid Offer.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1. THE PROPOSITIONS VVHICH THE MINISTERS <hi>OF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to maintaine againſt the Prelats.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1.<seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL matters meerely Eccleſiaſticall, which are lawfully impoſed vpon any Church, are ſuch as may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded neceſsarily from the writ ten word of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All Humane Ordinances vſed only or ſpecially in Gods worſhip, whervnto they are not neceſſary of them ſelues, are ſimply vnlawfull.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Euery true viſible Church of Chriſt is ſuch a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Body politike, as is ſpecially inſtituted by Chriſt or his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21472:7"/>Apoſtles in the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There is no True Viſible Church of Chriſt but a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ordinary Congregation onely.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Every true viſible Church of Chriſt, or ordinary Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of the faithfull, hath by Chriſts ordinance power in it ſelfe, immediatly under Chriſt, to elect and ordaine, deprive and depoſe their Miniſters, and to execute all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Paſtor of a particular Congregation is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ordinarie eccleſiaſticall Officer in any true conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted viſible Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="7">7. It is the Office of every true Paſtor to teach &amp; to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne ſpiritually onely one Church or Congregation im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mediatly under Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Paſtor alone ought not to exerciſe Eccleſiaſticall jurisdiction over his Church, but others ought to be joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Commisſion with him by the asſignement of the ſame Church; neither ought he and they to performe any maine and materiall Eccleſiaſticall act, without the free conſent of the Congregation.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Presbyterie which is deſired is not Lay, as they call it; And the Churchwardens and Sidemen heere in England, beyng joyned as Asſiſtants to the Miniſters in the overſight of the ſeverall Pariſhes, are a reſemblance of thoſe governing Elders which are deſired.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The Office and Calling of Provinciall &amp; Dioceſan Prelats is contrary to the word of God.</p>
               <p n="11">11. It is ſimply unlawfull for any Paſtor under the New Teſtament to be alſo a Civill Magiſtrat.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The Civill Magiſtrats ought to be the Overſeers of Provinces, &amp; Dioceſes, and of the ſeverall Churches ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: And it is their Office &amp; dutie injoyned them by God, to take knowledge of, to puniſh, and redreſſe all miſgover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21472:7"/>or ill teaching of any Church, or Church officer.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The Church government deſired is more agreable to the ſtate of a Monarchie, and to the Kings Supremacie in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, and more eaſie, and ſate both for Church &amp; Common wealth, then is the preſent govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Prelats.</p>
               <p n="14">14. No man hath authoririe to bring into the ſervice of God any Ceremony meerely Eccleſiaſticall, of myſticall ſignification.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The Ceremonies in controverſie are not indifferent, but contrary to the word of God.</p>
               <p n="16">16. The Miniſters refuſing the Conformitie and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription required, are therein neither Schiſmatiks, Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious perſons, enemyes to the Kings Supremacie, nor any way undutifull to King, or State.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The Conditions, forme, and maner of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or diſputation.</head>
               <p>THat there may be a free choiſe made by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters from amongſt themſelues of ſome 6. or 8. perſons, vnto whom the maintenance of theſe points may be committed; and as many choſen by the Prelats from among them ſelues, or their Conformed Clergie, to impugne the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it my be lawfull for thoſe on either ſide ſo cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, in any particular occurrent difficulty, to take counſell and aduiſe of any other their Brethren; and that then the ſpeciall acts of the ſaid choſen parties may be reputed the Acts of all thoſe that choſe them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That when one ſide hath oppoſed to the vttermoſt that they can, or ſhall ſee meet, then the other ſide ſhall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21472:8"/>oppoſe in like maner to the contrary: And that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates may (if they will) make choiſe which ſide ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in the firſt place.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the Opponents frame their Arguments in ſtrict forme of Syllogiſme only: And that the Anſwerers (without any excurſions, or perſonall ſpeeches whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer) anſwer directly to the premiſſes, either by denying or diſtinguiſhing; and that all be done in writing.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That if at any time the Anſwerer denying a Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ſhall withall giue a reaſon of his deniall, he doe it in few wordes: and that then the Opponent ſhall briefly by way of diſcourſe take away the reaſon, and after that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conclude the denied Propoſition; that ſo the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may come to the intended iſſue.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That if either in the Queſtion, Argument, or Anſwer there be any termes which ſhall ſeeme doubtfull, there be no proceeding in the Confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce untill the ſame be expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the explanations deliuered in writing, if they which make doubt ſhall require it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That neither ſide be urged to conclude thoſe clauſes, which in the maine Queſtions, or in the premiſſes of any Syllogiſme are without controverſie &amp; granted: but that by conſent they may be omitted, and that it may be only ſpecified briefely that ſuch or ſuch a clauſe in ſuch or ſuch a Propoſition is yeelded unto: And if there be many clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in one and the ſame propoſition which are doubtfull, that then it be lawfull and free to proue one of them after another.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That the Arguments, Anſwers, and Replyes be ſub ſcribed by every perſon of that ſide fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they com, and ſo delivered to the other ſide.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That there be no paſſing to the ſecond propoſition,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21472:8"/>vntill the firſt be fully debated, nor to the third vntill the ſecond &amp;c. As alſo, no paſſing to a ſecond or third argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vntill the firſt be followed to the vttermoſt.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That reaſonable time may be allowed for returning Replyes, &amp; Anſwers: and when any argument is proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the vttermoſt, that all the Syllogiſmes, Anſwers, &amp; Replyes be written together, and ſubſcribed by all parties of each ſide in the conference, as their ioynt act: and that after they are ſo ſubſcribed, there ſhall be no liberty to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or change any thing therein; But that before ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription it may be lawfull and free for each ſide vpon bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter conſiderations to alter, change, or revoke any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Reply, or Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That when theſe controverſies haue been debated to the vttermoſt, in maner and forme aforeſaide, two of each ſide be choſen to digeſt the whole into a booke; and that it may be publiſhed in Engliſh and Latin.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That all by controverſies and contentions whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, which ſhall fall out between the parties imployed in this conference, may be heard, iudged, determined, and ſentenced by ſome civill Magiſtrat aſsigned by his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That the ſaid Miniſters vndertaking this conference may haue publike warrant and protection from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie for the performance of the ſame, in ſuch maner as is heere ſet downe.</p>
               <p n="14">14. That if it plainly appeare by this indifferent triall (or by the Prelats refuſing to accept it) that the Miniſters in theſe Propoſitions haue the truth on their ſide, and that the Prelats are in ſo great error; Then the ſaid Miniſters &amp; as many els as ſhall ſee the truth which they ſtand for, may be exempted from the juriſdiction of the Prelats, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21472:9"/>reſtored agayne to their Miniſterie from which they haue been unjuſtly deprived, freed from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie and ſubſcription requyred, and may (with their particular Elderſhips &amp; Churches) be ſubject only to the authoritie and jurisdiction of the Civill Magiſtrate; to whom at all times they are willing and readie to yeeld an account of all their actions, and to humble themſelues un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their cenſures for any thing they ſhalbe found to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in; Conforming themſelues unto their willes in all things, alwayes, ſo farre as they may with a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and where they cannot ſo doe, ſubmitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to all ſuch puniſhment, as it ſhall pleaſe them to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon them.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That if it ſeeme not good to his Majeſtie &amp; the ſtate (for reaſons beſt knowne unto themſelues) to admit of ſo indifferent, honeſt, and reaſonable a Conference, yet it would pleaſe them to requyre the Prelats, to publiſh a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and full anſwer to ſuch bookes as haue (upon occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the late ſtormes) been publiſhed: viz. <hi>The Abridgement ſet forth by the Miniſters of Lincolne Dioceſe; The Demands, &amp; Conſiderations; Reaſons proving a neceſsitie of reforming our Churches in England; The old Proteſtant and New formaliſt; The Treatiſe of Divine worſhip; The</hi> 12 <hi>Arguments; The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Puritaniſme; and the Proteſtation &amp;c:</hi> And that it may be lawfull for the Miniſters modeſtly and directly to reply vnto the ſaid Anſwers, as alſo to any of the bookes which are lately, or haue been heertofore written againſt them &amp; their cauſe; and to publiſh the ſame in print with leaue of authority, which they under take and binde themſelues with all convenient ſpeed faithfully and honeſtly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme; they proteſting heere before Almightie God, the ſearcher of all hearts, and the juſt revenger of all hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21472:9"/>that (to their knowledge) there hath as yet no material thing been writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt them in theſe foreſaid Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or any other Controverſie betwixt them and the Prelats, but they are able to giue a reaſonable and juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply unto the ſame: and that by thoſe bookes, which haue been publiſhed againſt them, they haue been rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed &amp; ſtrengthened in the ſayd opinions which they hold againſt the Prelats, then any way ſatisfied or anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as ſhall appeare to all the world (by Gods gracious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance) if they may haue permitted unto them that liber tie, to publiſh their writings to the world, which the Pre lats take unto themſelues.</p>
               <p n="16">16. That if this moſt reaſonable and juſt courſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing theſe controverſies be denyed them, yet at leaſt they may haue free leaue to publiſh and to offer to the cenſure of the whole world nakedly and playnly, all thoſe ſeveral Arguments, &amp; Reaſons, which they haue thought upon for the confirmation of the former Propoſitions; as alſo their direct Anſwers to all ſuch Arguments on the contrary ſide, as they ſhall finde publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed in the writings of the Prelats and their adherents. In all which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to keepe themſelues cloſely &amp; directly to the poynts in controverſy, in ſo ſtrict a forme, that it ſhalbe moſt eaſy for the Prelats to giue an anſwer unto them, if ſo be they be in error in holding the ſaid Propoſitions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Iuſt Conſiderations moving the Miniſters to make this offer.</head>
               <p>MAny of the Miniſters having by reaſon of their Depoſition from the publike Miniſterie more cauſe, occaſion, and leaſure to ſtudie theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21472:10"/>then before, doe find that the more they wade into them, the more they are confirmed in that truth for which they ſuffer. So that howſoever the intendment of the Prelats hath been by their rigorous extremitie of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to make them to force their conſciences, againſt conſcience to yeeld, that ſo they might rejoyce in their fleſh; and though the Lord hath ſurrered their rod (to the further hardening of their hearts) to ly ſo heavie upon ſome of his ſervants that they haue put forth their hand to injquitie, yet otherſome by this meanes are ſo far from ſhrinking from the profeſſion of that truth which by their ſufferings they haue honored, that the more they haue ſuſtayned for it, the more (by the mercy of God) they ſee the glorious evidence of it. And therefore in honor vnto that heavenly truth they can do no leſſe, then in the feare of God make this offer vnto the greateſt enemyes therof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This cauſe, which the miniſters profeſſe and witnes vnto by their conſtant ſufferings, being (as they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in theire very ſoules and conſciences) a divine &amp; ſacred truth; and being notoriously reviled and blaſphem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed as a helliſh error by the mouthes of the prelats &amp; their favourers (one ſaying that <hi>he damned the diſcipline to Hell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence it came;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vaghan his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orie in uſes. Powel de diap. pref.</note> others publiſhing in print that <hi>Chriſt is not the Lawgiver of his Churh;</hi> all generally calling our doctrine and opinion in this cauſe, <hi>Schiſme</hi> and <hi>Haereſie,</hi> yea <hi>Treaſon and Rebellion;</hi> they having receaued this grace from God not only to ſee the truth heerein, but to ſeale and confirm it by their ſufferings, thinke it a moſt bounden duty that they owe vnto their Lord and maſter Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe Miniſters and Servants they are, by all good meanes to iuſtifie the ſame; yea though they neither had ſuffered nor ſhould ſuffer for it. Much more now, when as by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21472:10"/>providence of God, they haue in themſelues, their wiues, and children, ſuſtained &amp; indured ſo heavy things for it: And a more honeſt, moderat, Chriſtian, and religious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or Apology they cannot yeld vnto it, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by making ſuch an offer as this is, to the avowed enemyes thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is notorious vnto all the world, what indignities, ſianders, falſe accuſations, and calumniations, ouer and beſides the other Legall proceedings (as they are preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be) the Prelats and their adherents in their privat ſpeeches, publike ſermons, and writinges, lay vpon thoſe Miniſters that hold &amp; maintaine this cauſe, proclaiming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be <hi>Obſtinat &amp; Refractarie perſons, Enemyes to the King &amp; State, Notorious &amp; manifeſt Schiſmatikes, Turbulent ſpirits,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chaplin wel in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions.</note> 
                  <hi>Contemptuous and diſdayning the Authoritie of their lawfull Gouernors, preſumptuous and wilfull Contenders with the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat, Impugning his authority in thinges indifferent, and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie in Eccleſiaſticall cauſe, Falſe Prophets, Members rent and cut of from the Church of God, Runawayes from their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, ſome ſtanding vpon theſe points of difference not for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience but for carnall reſpects, ſom becauſe otherwiſe they knowe not how to be maintayned but by depending on that faction, ſom to gratify their benefactors &amp; patrons and to pleaſe their friends, ſom for diſcontentment and want of preferment, ſom for giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of innovation, ſom for pride of hart and ſelfeloue, ſom for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of order, and reſtraint of their libertie, ſom for ignorance, yet willfull, becauſe they will not knowe the ſtate of the queſtion, ſome to retaine the opinion of conſtancy, &amp;c.</hi> Now it being the duty of every Chriſtian even for Chriſts ſake and the Goſpells which he doth profeſſe, to cleere his innocencie againſt ſuch falſe and impious ſlanders; much more is it fit for the Miniſters of the Goſpell, being thus wickedly traduced, ſo to do. And therefore they think themſelues bound in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21472:11"/>conſcience to make this free and voluntarie offer vnto their Calumniators; the very propounding whereof is ſufficient to all honeſt and iuſt mindes, that do not will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhut their eyes againſt the truth, to cleere and free them from all the aforeſaid ſlanderous imputations.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Chriſtian and mercifull diſpoſition and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lower houſe of Parliament, and of ſundry of the Nobles of the Higher houſe (who in a holy Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration of the Miniſters diſtreſſed eſtates, and in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knowledge both of their honeſt liues and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and of the good they haue done in their Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and of their peaceable and duetifull behaviour to all in authoritie, haue been earneſt and zealous ſuppliants for them) hath been shamefully traduced by the Prelats; as though only through the incouragements &amp; hopes repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them, and for this cauſe ſpecially, that they might not be diſcredited and diſgraced in their indeavours and intendments for Reformation, the Miniſters did ſtand forth: Whereas by theſe preſents all the world ſhall know and underſtand, that the cauſe for which the Miniſters doe ſuffer is ſuch, as (all due thankfullnes and ſervice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to the Honorable and Chriſtian indeavour of the Parliament) though God ſhould (which we hope he will never permitt) ſo far forſake that High and Honorable Court, as in ſteed of being ſuppliants for the poore Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, they ſhould joyne with the Prelats in making the moſt rigorous lawes againſt them that might be (even to bloud) yet the Miniſters, by Gods good grace, ſtand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to hold and maintaine their ſaid profeſſion. In wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes whereof they publiſh to the view of all men, this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer as a teſtimony of their confident reſolution in the ſaid cauſe for which they ſuffer.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21472:11"/>
               <p n="5">5. There is ſuch indifferencie in this offer, and it ſtandeth upon ſo juſt &amp; equall grounds, that it ought not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed of any Chriſtians, no though made by <hi>Iewes, Turks, Arrians, Papiſts,</hi> or any other Heretiks whatſoever: Much leſſe when it is made by Miniſters conſtantly profeſſing &amp; ſhewing themſelues willing and readie to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in all things to the written word of God; and who in all matters (except in theſe Controverſies of Religion, wherein yet they agree with moſt of the Churches that haue made a ſeparation from Rome) are as obedient to the preſent State, and as unblameable in life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation as any other of his Majeſties ſubjects.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Divers of the aforeſaid Propoſitions are ſuch, as that if the Miniſters ſhould not conſtantly holde &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the ſame againſt all men, they cannot ſee how poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie (by the rules of Divinitie) the ſeperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches from the Church of Rome, and from the Pope, the ſupreme head thereof, can be juſtified. And therefore for aſmuch as in theſe controverſies the Papiſts and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats goe hand in hand, the ſaid Miniſters doe in like forme and maner make the like Offer to the Prieſts and Ieſuits, promiſing their reconcilement unto that Sea, if they can either by Arguments pull them from the foreſaid Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, or can anſwer ſuch Arguments as they ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound in the defence of them, in maner and forme before ſpecified in the Offer. And therefore it both ſtandes the Miniſters upon to make the aforeſaid Offer, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats (except they will haue all the world to judge them to be frends in heart to Popery) to accept of the ſame.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Doctors of <hi>Oxford</hi> in their anſwer to the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the 1000. Miniſters, and <hi>G. Powell</hi> in his laſt booke undertake the anſwer of whatſoever can be objected in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21472:12"/>theſe cauſes:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ook. pref. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>g 25.26.</note> and <hi>M. Hooker</hi> in his Preface before his firſt booke of <hi>Politiks,</hi> propoundeth unto the Miniſters that ſeeke Reformation the very like Offer and forme of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation: Which bookes were publiſhed with the ſpecial approbation of the Prelats. Wherefore the Miniſters ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been in ſuch a maner chalenged, they can doe no leſſe then make this offer; which cannot be refuſed of the Prelats, but they will be judged of all the world to offer that which they will not performe.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> with the conſent, and by the direction (no doubt) of ſome of the chiefeſt Prelats, hath now lately publiſhed his Sermon preached in Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember laſt before the King at <hi>Hampton Court;</hi> the maine drift wherof is to proue that the office &amp; calling of Dioce ſan Biſhops, in preſent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troverſie, is a Divine &amp; Apoſtoli call Ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: Beſids, in his epiſtle to the Miniſters of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land,</hi> prefixed before the ſayd Sermon, he profeſſeth that if there ſhall an anſwer be made therunto <hi>with modeſtie and learning, nothing ſhall be more welcome,</hi> And that <hi>to avouch &amp; make it good</hi> that the ſaid Epiſcopall calling is unlawfull, <hi>were a labor worthy the travell, and of the Prelats much deſired.</hi> Wherfore ſeeing the Prelats themſelues do offer to bring this cauſe to a publike triall (&amp; it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth us in England alſo no leſſ then our brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi>) &amp; ſeeing by this courſe &amp; order heere layd downe, this queſtion amongſt the reſt will come to be far more exactly tryed, then by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other way hitherto thought on, the Miniſters haue juſt cauſe to tender this Conference; nothing doubting but that the Prelats will willingly accept it, eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ſeeme ſo much to deſire it, and in all reaſon it is like to put an end to all theſe controverſies, which haue ſo long troubled the peace and quiet of our Churches.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21472:12"/>
               <p n="9">9. Since the Miniſters late troubles, there haue been many bookes publiſhed in Print againſt them, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning many ſhamefull untruthes and abuſes, wherin great violence &amp; wrong hath been offered to Gods truth; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny groſſe and Popiſh errors haue been divulged, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impoſtures uſed, onely to deceaue the ſimple, and to blind their eyes, that they may not ſee the truth of the Miniſters cauſe; which the Miniſters take themſelues bound in conſcience to anſwer. But being not able partly by reaſon of their povertie, partly by want of meanes of Printing, partly for other difficulties, to publiſh, ſo ſoone as is requiſit, ſo many anſwers (except they might haue leaue from authoritie) unto ſo many great bookes as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are: They haue judged it meet (in the meane time) to make this Offer, wherein if they prevaile &amp; gaine the cauſe, they make no queſtion but they ſhall haue all other particularities yeelded, and ſhall ſaue that other labor.</p>
               <p n="10">10. They haue warrant thus far from his Majeſtie, both in his booke called <hi>Basilicon doron;</hi> where he willeth them <hi>to preſse by patience and well grounded reaſons to perſwade other men to like of their iudgments;</hi> and by the Proclamation of <hi>Iuly</hi> 16. 1604: In which the Prelats are required to doe their uttermoſt indeavour by perſwaſions, Conference, Arguments, and all other wayes of gentlenes and loue to reclaime the Miniſters; which being as yet not done by them, can not be performed by a more direct and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent courſe, then by accepting ſuch an Offer as this is.</p>
               <p n="11">11. By direction from the chiefe of the Prelats,<note place="margin">Conſid. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>G. Powell</hi> hath publiſhed, That his excellent Majeſtie, <hi>as he loved theſe Miniſters dearlieſt of all others, ſo he ſought the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to reclayme them by ſome correction.</hi> So that either the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21472:13"/>Prelats heerein haue offered his Majeſtie open wrong in proclaiming his ſpeciall favor to the ſaid Miniſters, or elſe they are not to doubt, but in the abundance thereof he will vouchſafe to thoſe poore diſtreſſed and chaſtiſed favourits of his ſo much grace, as to command that this Offer may be accepted, and by his Royall aſſent to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the ſame.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The Apologeticall books which the Miniſters haue been conſtrayned from time to time to publiſh in defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their Perſons and Cauſe, can not come to the hands &amp; ſcanning of thoſe powers, that next under God are moſt able to relieue them. And therefore for the cleering of their innocencie and the juſtifiyng of their cauſe (which is indeed the cauſe of God) they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrayned to make this publike and ſolemne Offer, by meanes whereof it may come to paſſe that all men may take notice of the goodnes of the cauſe, and of the groſſe wrongs they haue ſuſtained and indured for maintayning the ſame.</p>
               <p n="13">13. His Majeſtie ſignified to the Committies of the Lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer houſe (Supplicating on the behalfe of the Miniſters) <hi>that before mercy there muſt goe a ſubmiſsion, and that if they looke for mercy at his hands, they muſt acknowledge a fault.</hi> This is that which they deſire; If it can be proved that they haue offended his Majeſtie in the leaſt thing, they deſire no mercy till they acknowledge a fault, and ſubmit them ſelues for the ſame. But it is (no doubt) far from the heart of ſo Royall a Prince to require either Confeſſion, or Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſion, wherther is no tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For their owne parts they are perſwaded and reſolved, that that truth for the profeſſing wherof the Prelats proceed ſo ſeverely againſt them, is moſt behoofull for his Majeſtie, his Crowne, and dignitie, and the whole State: And that in yeelding heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21472:13"/>in unto the Prelats, they ſhould make a breach in that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which by Gods law every true hearted and loyall ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ject in this kingdome oweth both to the King and State. And yet if they be in an errour, there can be no more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and likely courſe uſed to bring them unto a ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the ſame, then to haue theſe poynts freely debated by the acceptance of this Offer.</p>
               <p n="14">14. When the Miniſters conſider the dayly increaſe of Papiſts, their treacheries and conſpiracies, their inſolent bouldnes, the continuall broaching of groſſe and Popiſh errours, what litle moleſtation the Papiſts haue by the go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vernment of the Prelats, yea what favour they find ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly and under hand, what reſiſtance was made to the Lawes intended to haue been made againſt them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by ſome and thoſe not the meaneſt of the Prelats, what light matters are made of their horrible Treaſons and damnable opinions, what litle execution there is of the lawes againſt them; they haue reaſon to feare, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are aware &amp; as it were in a dreame, (if the raynes be in this maner left in the Prelats handes for matters of religion) the neck both of his Royall Maieſtie and of the whole State ſhalbe brought under the yoke of the Pope that Antichriſt of Rome, and his diveliſh jdolatrie. And therefore in a ſerious mediatation of the beſt meanes to prevent this great &amp; imminent evill, which lyeth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in a myſterie, they cannot thinke of a more direct courſe then this open and profeſſed Oppoſition unto the Prelats in the foreſaid Propoſitions; wherein if they ſhall prevaile, they ſhall not onely giue a deadly wound to the Prelacie it ſelfe, but to the accurſed Religion of Rome, from which (at leaſt, if it be held to be <hi>Iure divino</hi>) it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaveth both breath and life. For who was ſo ſimple that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21472:14"/>ſaw not, that at his Majeſties firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the Crowne when the Prelats hangd downe their heads in ſuſpenſe &amp; feare, the Papiſts hearts were as dead as ſtones; and that the very firſt Proclamation againſt the Miniſters in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Prelats, revived the Papiſts againe: And that ever ſince with the increaſe of the grace, favour, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Prelats, the hopes, bouldnes, and nombers of Papiſts haue increaſed. And therefore howſoever the Prelats may mocke children and fooles in imputing the Miniſters; yet any that wiſheth the confuſion of that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt may with halfe an eye ſee, where the true cauſe is. And therefore they ſeeing this (except they ſhould be wilfull traytors to God, their King, and Country) cannot but make oppoſition unto the Prelats in approving the Propoſitions aboue ſpecified: wherein if they be in an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and the Prelats on the contrary haue the truth; they proteſt to all the world that the Pope and the Church of Rome (and in them God and Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe) haue had great wrong &amp; indignitie offered unto them, in that they are rejected; and that all the Proteſtant Churches are Schiſmaticall in forſaking Unitie and Communion with them.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The former Propoſitions are ſuch, that there will not be found (as we are verily perſwaded in our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences) any one Conformable Miniſter in this kingdome, except he be a masked Papiſt, that will refuſe to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to any one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if ſo be it would pleaſe the King and State by Law to urge them thereunto under ſuch penalties as the Miniſters are urged to ſubſcribe unto the Articles deviſed by the Prelats. Yea, we are out of all doubt, that the Prelats themſelues (if it were preſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21472:14"/>them by the King and ſtate vnder paine of deprivatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from their Biſhopricks) would not ſtick to avouch vpon their othes, that the Ceremonies and Subſcription, for which the Miniſters ſtand ſuſpended and deprived, are wicked and vngodly, &amp; ſuch as no good Chriſtian ought to yeeld vnto. Nay, if the caſe ſtood but vpon the ſauing of their Temporaltyes thereby (which elſe they ſhould looſe) we doubt not but they would with heart &amp; hand ſubſcribe to any one of the aforeſaid Propoſitions. Sith therefore it is more then cleere, that they haue Offered plaine violence vnto the Conſciences of all moſt all the conforming and ſubſcribing Miniſters; &amp; that even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to their owne conſciences they haue proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their poore bretheren, becauſe they will not by conformitie &amp; ſubſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ption renounce the truth contayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe propoſitie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; can any blame the ſaid Miniſters, if hauing not only the ſaid truth on their ſide, but in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood the Conſciences of the Prelats alſo, they make ſuch an Offer as this is?</p>
               <p n="15">15. It is agreeable to common ſenſe and reaſon (and the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> hath ſome ſuch thing in his Le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctures vpon the Commandements) that doubtfull acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould all-wayes giue place vnto thoſe that are out of all doubt &amp; queſtion. Seeing therefore no good Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ever doubted, but that it is lawfull enough in it ſelfe to adminiſter the word and ſacraments in common and ordinary civill attyre, to adminiſter Baptiſme without the ſigne of the Croſſe or any ſuch like myſticall rite, and to vndertake a Miniſtery (being called thervnto of the Church) without the authority of a Dioceſan Prelate, and without any ſuch ſubſcription as is required: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the conſormity and ſubſcription required (againſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21472:15"/>which the Miniſters doe witnes) hath been ever called into queſtion ſince the firſt appearance of the Goſpell out of Popery, &amp; concluded and determined againſt, both in the profesſion and practis of the greateſt lights of this age, and of ſo many Reformed Churches; haue not the Miniſters juſt cauſe (they deſiring nothing which is of it ſelfe vnlawful, &amp; ſuffering for nothing but for the refuſall of thoſe things which haue ever been in Controverſy, whether they be lawfull or not) haue not the Miniſters (we ſay) juſt cauſe to make this Offer, and to cleaue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly vnto that which all men grant to be lawfull, vntill by ſome ſuch indifferent meanes as this is, the contrary matters, bejng ſo doubtfull, ſhall be proved to be lawfull.</p>
               <p n="16">16. It is notorious vnto all the world what damnable and impious imputations the Prelats and their defendors haue laid vpon <hi>Calvin, BeZa,</hi> and all reformed Churches, raking vp calumniations againſt them out of the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>Allen, Parſons,</hi> and other traiterous Papiſts, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Biſhop <hi>Iewel</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> haue moſt cleerly in their writings againſt the Papiſts detected the falſhood thereof. And ſeeing that the Papiſts haue gone about, ſince the diſcovery of that late deteſtable plot by gunpowder, to iuſtifie their abominable Treaſons, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, Rebellions, Periuries, and Equivocations by the doctrine of the worthyeſt Proteſtants, taking iuſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereof by the ſlanderous writings of the Prelats againſt thoſe of our owne religion; And further ſeeing that the intent of the Prelats therin was to make all the Miniſters, that conſent in iudgment with thoſe perſons and Churches which they haue thus traduced, odious and vile in the eyes of all men, as perſons in clined to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous conſpiracies, Treaſons, and Rebellions; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21472:15"/>no other ground, nor any colour of all this, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe together with other Churches they holde the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid propoſitions; howſoever in a late Reply vnto the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts the matter be pittifully ſhifted of: yet ſeeing theſe heavy proceedings againſt the ſaid Miniſters are a kinde of confirmation of the aforeſaid imputations, it ſtands them vpon by this Offer to cleere themſelues, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the vnchriſtian and vngodly wrongs which the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats haue don to ſo many worthy perſons &amp; Churches.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Vpon a ſerious conſideration how the hand of God hath been vpon many of thoſe, who, hauing formerly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced this cauſe, haue ſhrunk from tre truth maintained in theſe propoſitions; how ſome of them haue evidently loſt the grace and power of their gifts, ſome growen to be idle, neglecting both privat and publike dutyes, yea pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and ſcandalous in their liues and converſations, ſom aſhamed to ſhew their faces in the preſence of any who truly fearing God haue knowne their former cariage, ſom languiſhing and pining away till they haue died, &amp; that within few dayes after their yeelding, ſome poſſeſſed (as it were) with a continuall fury inceſſantly vexing &amp; tormen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting them,<note place="margin">FR. MAR</note> and thruſting them into continual ſtorming &amp; raging in the pulpit aginſt thoſe that doe not as they do, all of them falling to the maintenance of moſt groſſe and Popiſh errors, and none of them reſpected allmoſt by any, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned &amp; ſcorned even of the Prelats themſelues, as thoſe which were either hypocrits before, or hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crits now; The Miniſters hauing receaved this grace from God, not only to ſee and acknowledge this truth, but to confirme it with their ſufferings, haue thought it more then needfull to make this Chriſtian Offer, for the ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtrengthening of ſuch of their brethren, as are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21472:16"/>in danger to fall after the ſame maner.</p>
               <p n="18">18. In as much as all the profeſſed and notorious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, Papiſts, Blaſphemers, Adulterers, Drunckards, &amp; infamous perſons in this Kingdome, are together with the prelats profeſſed enemyes vnto the Miniſters in this cauſe, and haue been from time to time the ſpeciall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of all the troubles which haue befallen them for the ſame; can any man lay any iuſt blame vpon the Miniſters for making this Offer, now, when as the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats haue by their late proceedings giuen ſuch cauſe to all the wicked and profane of the land to clappe their hands in Triumph over them?</p>
               <p n="19">19. It is well knowen in thoſe Countries where the ſaid Miniſters haue liued, eſpecially to the Townes where they haue exerciſed their Miniſtery, that, according to the proportion of their Livings and maintenance, they haue kept as good hoſpitalitie, given as liberall intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto others, and as much relieved (to their power) thoſe in want, as any other Miniſters whoſoever; whereas now a great part of them, with their wiues and children, are forced to liue vpon the beneuolence and devotions of others. Which lamentable and miſerable aſtate of theirs, the Prelats and their Adherents are ſo far from pitying, that they take occaſion the more to ſcorne &amp; deride the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea and to inſult over them for the ſame: they being not aſhamed both in the Pulpit &amp; in Print falſely to affirme, that by this meanes not only the outward eſtate of the Miniſters is bettered, but that they haue voluntarily and of ſet purpoſe left their Miniſtery, that they might liue in this maner vpon the ſweat of other mens browes, and by Contributions inrich themſelues. Though therfore the many &amp; great meanes, which the Miniſters haue vſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21472:16"/>both to prevent theſe proceedings, and to be reſtored to their places againe, are ſufficient to lay open the ſhame of theſe malicious &amp; ſpitfull calumniations; Yet they have thought it meet by this Offer to make it knowne unto all the world, that they are ſo far from affecting ſuch a courſe of life, that they ever haue been, and are ſtill, moſt willing to doe any thing (but that, the doing whereof may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure damnation unto their ſoules) for the keeping or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of their former places, from which they haue been thruſt; to the end that they might eaſe their Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an friends of thoſe great burdens, wherewith ſince theſe late troubles they haue been preſſed, in yeelding reliefe unto their extremities.</p>
               <p n="21">21. The Prelats are now come to this height of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh injquitie,<note place="margin">G. Powel Adiaph. c. 2. ſect. 7.8.9.10:</note> that they are not aſhamed to hold &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, <hi>that they being the Church, are in their Canons and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions alwayes directed</hi> in externall thinges <hi>by the ſpirit of God; and that therefore whatſoever they decree is more then Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, yea even Divine; and that the true Church allwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the word, ſo as it cannot poſsibly ſwarue from the ſame; and therefore all her Traditions are holy and divine.</hi> And this Church of Prelats (profeſſing themſelves to be <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in a ſacred Synod in the name of Chriſt,</hi> and directed by the ſpirit of God,<note place="margin">Canon 13</note> 
                  <hi>and Excommunicating all them that ſhall ſay the contrary</hi>) haue in their ſaid late Synod decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that all who ſhall affirme, that either <hi>the Ceremonyes in Controverſie are ſuperſtitious and unlawfull,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Can: 6, &amp;</note> 
                  <hi>or that the Government by Archbiſhops and Biſhops is not</hi> Apoſtolicall and <hi>lawfull,</hi> are to be excommunicated <hi>ipſo facto.</hi> Now ſeeing that not onely the Miniſters ſuſpended and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, but many thowſand others in this Kingdome, do affirme and maintaine theſe things, they ſtand all by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21472:17"/>of thoſe Canons Excommunicat, and ſtanding in that eſtate (if juſtly) are by conſequence in the caſe of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea ſo as (dying reſolutly in theſe poynts) they muſt needes be damned everlaſtingly. Either therefore the Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lats ſhall ſhew themſelues to be Antichriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that in a high degree, in ſending without any mercy or compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo many thowſand ſoules, with the daſh of a pen, to Hell, it being in their power to keepe them out; or excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly preſumptuous, in denouncing ſuch a ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cannot but know &amp; oftentimes do confeſſe, to be the true ſervants of God; or at the leaſt it ſtandeth them upon diligently to uſe all good meanes for the recovery of ſo many ſoules out of Hell, eſpecially then, when, by ſuch an Offer as this is, they hold up their hands out of the pit, deſiring to be pulled out.</p>
               <p n="22">22 Laſt of all, the Propoſitions being ſo plainly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly layd downe, and ſo directly oppoſite to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Prelats; they having alſo ſo often diſgraced the Miniſters for their paucitie, and povertie of gifts and learning, and ſo often vaunted of the multitudes of great learned men on their ſide, and by that meanes having far greater choyſe of ſufficient and able men then the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters haue; and being better able to furniſh them with all needfull helps to ſuch a worke, and the poynts in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie ſo neerely touching their Iurisdiction, ſtate, and dignitie, which is ſo deare and pretious unto them; alſo the Offer that is made unto them being ſo equall, juſt, and Chriſtian, if they ſhall refuſe to yeeld unto the ſame, &amp; in ſteed thereof afflict the perſons which humbly make this Offer unto them, they ſhall therein proclaime to all the world, that in theſe their proceedings they haue ſinned &amp; doe ſinne with a high hand and malicious heart, (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21472:17"/>to knowledge and conſcience) againſt God and his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truth: and therefore are to be judged to be at the next dore of committing that unpardonable ſinne, which the Prelats, in the time of our Saviour Chriſts being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, in the like caſes committed. From which if it be the good will of God (notwithſtanding all the evill which they haue done againſt theſe poore ſervants of Chriſt, and the Churches of God committed to their charge) they pray carneſtly that they may quit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and that, upon their repentance in this life, they may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine unto ſuch a crowne of glory, as they in their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are perſwaded is layd up for ſome of thoſe, whom they uſe now living in the world as Heathens &amp; Infidels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4. AN ANSWER TO SVCH <hi>OPPO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SITIONS, AS MAY BE MADE BY THE</hi> Prelats, againſt yeelding to the aforeſaid Offer.</head>
               <div n="1" type="opposition">
                  <head>1. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The reverend Fathers of the Church, before they proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſuſpenſion and deprivation of the Miniſters, uſed godly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, exhortations, &amp; arguments to perſwade them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie, anſwering whatſoever they could then obiect, why they ſhould not conforme. Therefore what neede they now to enter into that trouble againe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is not true.
<list>
                        <item>I. They neuer vſed any one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to the purpoſe, but ſuch as hath been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently anſwered we know not how often.</item>
                        <item>2. Their <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21472:18"/>Admonitions were meere formall; wherin alſo the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters were exceedingly wronged: divers of them (who were very poore men, and ſome of their livings not aboue 40. ſom 30. ſome 20. pounds by the yeare, &amp; their charge of wife, children, and family very great) being forced to come in the depth of winter 9. or 10. times, yea ſome ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, unto their Pallaces, ſome of them 30. ſome 40. ſome 50. miles and more to receaue their Admonitions, and at length their deprivations for their labor.</item>
                        <item>3. We deſire <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that the Prelats would publiſh to the view of all the world thoſe Arguments which they uſed, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters did not, or could not anſwer.</item>
                        <item>4. This is a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine truth, &amp; wilbe juſtified to the faces of them all, that many of the Miniſters demanded of them Reaſons and Arguments, according to the forme of the Kings Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and they refuſed to giue any: yea divers of them ſundry times offered their Propoſitions, and Reaſons to the Prelats, promiſing, upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their reaſonable anſwer, with out any further queſtion to Conforme; and to this day they never gaue them any.</item>
                        <item>5. This may the more incite <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> them to accept of this Offer: for by this meanes they may make knowne to the world thoſe great Arguments and Reſolutions, which then they uſed, and may ſet them downe with mature and adviſed deliberation, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of their proceedings.</item>
                        <item>6. The only Argument to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> that they uſed, was this, that it was his Majeſties plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure it ſhould be ſo: thereby laying the imputation and envie of their unjuſt proceedings upon him.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="opposition">
                  <head>2. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Miniſters can ſay noe more then they haue ſaid &amp; writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21472:18"/>already, and which we haue anſwered often. And why then ſhould we try theſe things any further?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. This is more then the Prelats know. Some of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſters <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> haue lately ſaid more to ſome poynts, then hath been ſaid before. And upon ſuch occaſions as may be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by ſuch a Conference, they may ſay more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue ſaid yet.</item>
                     <item>2. The prelats, by their corrupt anſwers in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> their late publiſhed writings, haue given them occaſion to ſay more, then yet hath been ſaid.</item>
                     <item>3. This they are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> able to make good, that that which they haue ſaid alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, hath not been anſwered as yet; and therfore this Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is deſired that theſe matters may be further tried.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="opposition">
                  <head>3. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is dangerous that matters eſtabliſhed by Law ſhould be thus called into queſtion, and diſputed of as matters doubtfull.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Theſe matters are not now newly called into ques<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> but they haue been from time to time oppoſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and ſo will be to the end of the world; at leaſt wiſe ſo long as ſo many Churches of God in other Kingdoms profeſſe and practiſe as they doe; and the rather becauſe many great and famous Lights of the Church, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Seas and at home, in their Monuments that ſhall laſt to all poſteritie, haue teſtifyed againſt them. This therefore is not to call a matter, which is out of queſtion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21472:19"/>into queſtion, but to call a matter already in queſtion, to a direct and finall determination.</item>
                     <item>2. It cannot but be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> very profitable vnto any State (ſuch rules and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as are here propounded, being obſerved) to debate and diſpute, in ſuch a maner as this is, of any humane law whatſoever. For by this meanes, if a law be iuſt, it wilbe an honor vnto it to haue the iuſtice therof manifeſted; if vniuſt, it may be abrogated. And how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth it to paſſe, that ſo many lawes of man are abrogated by man, if whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once a Law is enacted, it may not be called into queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Iuſt Lawes grounded vppon equitie, reaſon, &amp; the word of God never dread examination, but vniuſt and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Lawes do.</item>
                     <item>3. Theſe matters were never yet ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> eſtabliſhed by law, as is pretended, but only tolerated: it being the intent of the firſt retainers of theſe Reliques of popery, in time to aboliſh them. And ſince the 14. yere of hir late Maieſties Raigne, the High Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and the ſtate of this Kingdome (who only, with the aſſent of the King, haue power to make and abrogate Lawes, whether Civill or Eccleſiaſticall) haue euer ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelues readie to eaſe the Churches of theſe burd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, which vnder the name of things eſtabliſhed by Law are impoſe vpon them by the Prelats. Only the Prelars, hauing many voyces of their owne in the vpper Howſe, haue, by their groſſe flatteryes &amp; fayned promiſes to the in Chiefe place, ever croſſed the holy endeavors of the Parliament for the removall of theſe burdens, grievous both to Church and Commonweale.</item>
                     <item>4. It is ordinary <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> in our Univerſities to admit of argumentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt any poynt of Religion and Faith; and that in ſuch a maner, as is more dangerous to the truth, and leſſe indifferent, then this forme that is heere offered.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21472:19"/>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="opposition">
                  <head>4. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If Schiſmaticks and factious perſons may haue this favour, why then may not Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, and Papiſts exſpect the ſame?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. They Miniſters deny themſelues to be Schiſmatiks, &amp; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſhall at any time iuſtifie themſelues to be as honeſt men, and as dutifull &amp; loyall ſubjects as any Prelat in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</item>
                     <item>2. The thing they deſire is no favor, but that which in juſtice is to be yeelded vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Neither ſhall they get <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> any good, but hurt by it, except the truth be on their ſide.</item>
                     <item>3. It were a ſhame for a ſtate profeſſing the true Religion publikly, to deny to the free ſubiects thereof, deſiring it, ſuch an indifferent hearing of their opinions, as this is, be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> they of the Separation, or Anabaptiſts, or what they may be. For if the Heathen had not, much leſſe ſhould true Chriſtans haue any ſuch law, to condemne any ſect or faction whatſoever, before they heare them: and heare them they doe not, that will refuſe to admit of ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Offer as this is. And it is a ſhame of ſhames to the Doctors of Oxford, who provoking thoſe whom they call Browniſts, in their Anſwer to the Miniſters Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, and being challenged of dishoneſtie and iniuſtice in an Anſwer therevnto, have not in all this time iuſtified themſelues, &amp; anſwered that which the other ſay in their owne defence; it being ſo grauely, moderatly, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly ſet downe. How much greater ſhame &amp; reproch would it be, to refuſe ſuch a direct kinde of triall as this is, tyed to ſo ſtrict rules, ſo preiudiciall to error, &amp; of ſo great
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21472:20"/>advantage to the truth.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="opposition">
                  <head>5. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Offer argues only a willfull obſtinacie of perſons that will never be ſatisfied, and content with reaſon. For was not (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their owne ſeeking) their cauſe handled &amp; heard in the Conference at Hampton Court, his Maieſtie him ſelfe moderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the action, and anſwering whatſoever, in theſe points their owne Agents could obiect? what would they more?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. In their objecting to the Miniſters the Conference at Hampton Court, they object to them, as it were, that which is <hi>Non Ens:</hi> None of them knowing what it was, nor any other faue a few that were preſent, whoſe reports thereof are alſo ſo diuerſe, that one ſpoyles the credit of another. And that which is ſet forth as the true report of it, being publiſhed onely by the Prelates (who are parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all) without the knowledge, aduiſe, or conſent of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, deſerues no credit; the rather conſidering that <hi>D. Morton</hi> hath bene allowed to call ſome part of it into queſtion, even ſome ſpeeches fathered vpon his Maieſtie, which he was faine to confute as vnſound and contrary to divinitie. Wherin ſith the Kings owne ſpeeches be, as it ſeemeth, groſſely abuſed by the author, it is much more likly that ſpeeches of other men are abuſed. Beſides, none but Prelats, and ſuch as were partiall, being preſent at the firſt dayes Conference, there can be no credit at all given to the report thereof: for it is more then apparant, that they haue fraudulently cut of, and concealed all the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21472:20"/>ſpeeches (which were many) that his Maieſtie vttered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of our Church, &amp; practiſe of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lats: as appeareth by that teſtimony of the Deane of the Chappell, which he gaue therof, ſaying, <hi>That his Maieſtie did that day wonderfully play the Puritan.</hi> But if he playd that part no otherwiſe then is ſpecified in the Prelats re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, he acted it very poorely, or rather never a whitt. If therefore they would haue had the Miniſters to ſtand to the determination of that Conference, they ſhould haue vſed more indifferencie and honeſtie in the Relation of it, then they haue don; they ſhould at leaſt haue made it appeare by mutuall teſtimonie of all ſides, that it was a true act. For they haue no reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to belieue ſuch enemies, as the Prelats haue ſhewed themſelues to be vnto them, any further then they ſee them.</item>
                     <item>2. Such a conference as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that, was never deſired by the Miniſters; And it ſeemes by the whole managing of it, that it was vnderhand plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and procured by the Prelats themſelues; abuſing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Maieſtie, and vſing M. Galloway as an inſtrument in the matter, to the end that they might haue the more colour for their intended proceedings afterwards. And there is great probabilitie of this, for that the Archbiſhop profeſſed to the Committies of both Howſes, the laſt ſes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that he had the letters written from M. Cartwright to M. Galloway about that matter.</item>
                     <item>3. Moſt of the perſons, appoynted to ſpeake for the Miniſters, were not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of their choſing, nor nomination, nor of their iudgment in the matters then and now in queſtion, but of a cleane contrary. For being intreated at that time by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to diſpute againſt theſe things, as things ſimply evill and ſuch as cannot be yeelded vnto without ſinne; they profeſſed to them, that they were not ſo perſwaded, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21472:21"/>therefore could not ſo doe. Being then requeſted, to let his Majeſty underſtand that ſome of their brethren were further perſwaded touching the unlawfulnes of theſe things, then themſelues were; they refuſed that alſo. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being intreated either to giue them in writing their rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons to proue theſe thinges indifferent, or to giue them an anſwere in writing to ſuch reaſons as they would giue them in writing, to proue them ſimply euill; they would doe neither the one nor the other; ſo that there neither was, nor could be any hope of good by that conference.</item>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. The matters in controverſy were not in that Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence throughly debated, but nakedly propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, &amp; ſom not at all touched: neither was there any one Argument <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> to the purpoſe followed in the ſame.</item>
                     <item>5. The Prelats took vnto them ſelues liberty to interrupt, at their pleaſure, thoſe of the other ſide; inſomuch that they were checked <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> for it by his Maieſtie.</item>
                     <item>6. The Miniſters (if his Maieſtie will giue them leaue) will at any time, in one weeks ſpace, deliuer to his Maieſtie in writing a full anſwere to any Argument, or Aſſertion, propounded in that Conference againſt them by any Prelate: and they do here plainely profeſſe that all and every one of them are moſt vaine and frivolous.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="opposition">
                  <head>6. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe Miniſters, by oppugning the Prelats, doe openly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the Government of his Maieſtie, and the whole State: and therefore noe ſuch favor is to be yeelded to them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. If the aforeſaid Propoſitions be all of them true, &amp;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21472:21"/>ſuch as will be iuſtifyed by the written word of God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Miniſters (who heerein ſeeke nothing but the bare defence of that truth contayned in them, which is of ſo great importance) cannot be truly charged with any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifull behavior toward King or State: if they be not true, this tryall will make it manifeſt to all men, and that to the greater ſhame of theſe Miniſters.</item>
                     <item>2. They doubt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> not (whatſoever the Prelats ſhall intimate to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) but that this Conference will much redound to the Honor of his Maieſties perſon, and Governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For by it that truth ſhall appeare, which (how ſoever it hath been generally receaved in other Churches abroad) hath been hitherto either vnknowen among vs, or much obſcured by the Prelats &amp; their friends; albeit it doth indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, and that deeply, the true ordinary meanes of ſaving our ſoules.</item>
                     <item>3. The Miniſters are heerein ſo far from ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to diſgrace the King or his Gouernment, that they would eſteeme it a ſingular blesſing of God, if they might be ſo happy, as to obtaine that the aforeſaid Propoſitions (containing in them the nature of Chriſts true Viſible Church, Miniſterie, and Worſhip) may, by his Maieſties ſpeciall order and appointment, be examined and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, in ſuch a moſt reaſonable and vnpartiall Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as before is tendered: wherevnto they make no queſtion but they ſhall finde his Maieſtie willing inough, if the Prelats do not vnder hand procure him to hinder it.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="opposition">
                  <head>7. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is not meet that the Governors of the Church ſhould in this maner debaſe themſelues vnto ſuch meane and privat perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21472:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. They are no privat perſons, being publike Minis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Goſpell; and diuers of them of as good eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Schooles for their knowledge in Divinitie and Humanitie, and as reverend for their yeares, as any of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Prelats are.</item>
                     <item>2. Some of the principall of the Prelats haue already more diſgraced themſelues in this kinde, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhould by yeelding to ſuch a Conference as this is. The Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> (as is well knowen) vndertooke the Anſwer of <hi>M. Iacobs</hi> laſt booke. The Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> profeſſed openly in his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtory, that he would <hi>ſhake out of the raggs</hi> that booke, which the Miniſters of <hi>Lincolne</hi> Dioces delivered to his Maieſtie, the <hi>Abridgment</hi> whereof is publiſhed in print. Doctor <hi>Felton</hi> alſo at the requeſt of the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> vndertooke to anſwer the <hi>Treatiſe of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip:</hi> which bookes maintaine and defend in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the aforeſaid propoſitions. And though two years are now allmoſt paſt, yet noe Anſwer to any of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth.</item>
                     <item>3. The Prelats may choſe whether themſelues <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> will perſonally deale in the Conference or not; they may asſigne heerevnto their ordinarie Champions, who haue for their preferment alreadie put forth themſelues in the cauſe: And who (for greater hopes) wilbe ready to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe this ſervice.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="opposition">
                  <head>8. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This very Offer is enough to iuſtifie the former proceeding; of the Reverend Fathers againſt the Miniſters, and to manifeſt how intolerable they are in this ſtate. They pretended, in their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21472:22"/>firſt Petition to his Maieſty no deſire of innovation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but only the remouall of a few Ceremonies, and ſome other ſuppoſed corruptions. Now they haue manifeſted their hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie to all the world; which the Biſhops foreſeeing thought it needfull to take this courſe againſt them. For nothing will ſatisfy theſe fellowes, but either the overthrowe of Biſhops, or at leaſt wiſe their freedome from them. And therefore can any blame the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, if they giue them the ſame meaſure, that they, if they had the power in their hands, would mete vnto them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. If the Miniſters doe now cut deeper at the roote of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the Prelacie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heretofore they haue done, it is becauſe, ſince their late proceedings, they haue ſeene more into the myſterie of injquitie, that worketh in their ſpirituall Dominion, then ever they ſaw before: And therfore they muſt thanke themſelues for it.</item>
                     <item>2. It is now made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to the whole world, that there is no hope of freedom from the ſpirituall bondage of Antichriſtian Traditions, ſo long as the Prelats ſit in their Thrones, but a more dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expectation of greater ſlaverie and ſervitude, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before, as may appeare by the late <hi>Canons</hi> and their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceedings. And therefore howſoever ſome reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Miniſters nouriſh ſtill many hopes, that the Prelats will at length ſhew mercy, and be content to let them in joy the libertie of their conſciences, and ſuffer them to exerciſe a Miniſterie under them; yet they that make this Offer ſeeing no likelyhood nor poſſibilitie of any ſuch matter, but of the cleane contrarie (the Prelats having in ſo high a degree blaſphemed and perſecuted this truth of God) they thinke themſelues now bound in conſcience
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21472:23"/>by all honeſt &amp; good meanes to ſeeke to be freed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that eſtate, which cannot (as it appeares now to all the world) uphold it ſelfe,<note place="margin">G. Powel Adiaph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ef.</note> but by the ruine of the Goſpell, and exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Antichriſtianiſme.</hi> For they that plead for their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Traditions are driven to hold theſe impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and irreligious Abſurdities;<note place="margin">D. Covil, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ainſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ea of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>n: pa. 19.</note> *That <hi>Chriſt is not the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver of his Church:!</hi> That <hi>it is a vertuous obedience, to reſt as well in that which the Church commandeth unto us, as in that which God commandeth to his Church:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hutton, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> the Croſſ, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>g 3.4</note> "That <hi>the Church is ruled by the ſpirit of Chriſt, who is the truth; and therefore her Traditions are true and holy:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hooker, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ef. pag 28.</note> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> That <hi>God alloweth men to doe that which in their private iudgment it ſeemeth; yea and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps truely ſeemeth,<note place="margin">B. Roch. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ermon at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ampton <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ourt, p. 31.</note> that the Law doth diſallow.</hi> § That <hi>vnwrit ten</hi> Ordinances, aſwell as <hi>written,</hi> are Divine and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike in the conſtitution of the chiefeſt Office, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of the Church.</item>
                     <item>3. They doe no further deſire <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> their freedom from the Prelats, &amp; from that power which they haue, then they ſhall be able to proue, that it is lifted up againſt the Doctrine and Kingdome of Chriſt our Lord.</item>
                     <item>4. They leaue their overthowe to God and the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> King; and doe only by theſe premiſſes labor, that that truth, which hath been amongſt vs long ſuppreſſed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, may come to light, and may be ſo honored and freed at laſt, as God requireth that it ſhould be.</item>
                     <item>5. If the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Callings of the Prelats be warrantable, and of Divine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance (as Biſhop <hi>Barlow</hi> avoucheth in his late Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) then the yeelding vnto this Offer wilbe a notable meanes to eſtabliſh the ſame, and can no wayes be dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory vnto it: for no Divine ordinance will fly or feare any ſuch Tryall. But if it be vnlawfull (as it will be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all men to be, even in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences of the Prelats, if they ſhall refuſe this Offer) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indeed this Tryall can
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21472:23"/>be no meanes to iuſtify the Prelats, who ought in ſuch a caſe either to giue ouer their places, or at leaſt to ſuffer thoſe, that haue their conſciences perſwaded of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulnes of their Callinges, to be free, even as Chriſt hath made them free both from them and their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="opposition">
                  <head>9. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Offer proceeds from them who wilbe ſatisfyed with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. If they ſhould haue the Diſcipline granted them, and all that they deſire, they would not ſtay there; that would not conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them. At the firſt they ſtood vpon a few Ceremonies only; after this they cryed downe with Biſhops; and when they haue their de ſire in this, then let the King looke to himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. This is but a malicious ſurmiſe of that whereof there <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is noe ground; the Propoſitions before ſet downe make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it more then manifeſt, that as the Miniſters haue not any the leaſt intention to impeach the Royall dignity, ſo likewiſe they doe much more advance the ſame indeed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prelats do.</item>
                     <item>2. The practiſe of all other Reformed <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Churches, inioying the Diſcipline which is deſired, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futeth this ſlanderous obiection; in as much as they reſt content under the ſame without ſeeking, or indeauoring, any vaine or rebellious innovation.</item>
                     <item>3. Though ſome Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> haue ſtoode upon the Ceremonies onely, yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them haue from time to time witneſſed vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in ſpeciall maner againſt the Prelacie, according as God hath opened their underſtanding in this point,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21472:24"/>though ſom of them at the firſt did not ſufficiently conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how unlawfull and unwarrantable it is: and this is no more preiudiciall either to them or to the cauſe, then it was to the Apoſtle Paul for teaching that doctrine after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which at firſt he underſtood not: or to thoſe now profeſſing the Goſpell, who in times paſt haue bene igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Papiſtes, &amp; enemies to the trueth.</item>
                     <item>4. The Miniſters de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſire not that either the Diſcipline, or any thing els ſhould be yeelded unto them, or that they ſhould haue their willes ſatiſfied in any thing, further then they are able to proue the thing (for want whereof they are unſatiſfied) to be due unto them by the word of God. And ſo far forth they thinke it lawfull for them, or any els, to ſhew themſelues unſatiſfied: it being a grieuous Sinne for any, in matters of Religion and meanes of Saluation, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelues with leſſe, then God will haue them to be content withall. The Ordinances of God will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent them ſufficiently; and nothing will diſcontent them but to be depriued of any of the ſame, they all being ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meanes of Saluation. And is it not an Antichriſtian ſpirit, that would binde men to any other Content? If in their diſcontent they deſire any thing that God doth not require them to deſire, there may be as many meanes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> found then, as now, to bridle their deſires.</item>
                     <item>5. Their adviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King to looke to himſelfe, when Ceremonies &amp; Dioceſan Biſhops are downe, is a Scarcrow, fitter to fright Dawes away, then to hinder ſo wiſe a Majeſty from yeelding his furtherance to ſo Chriſtian an Offer. The Miniſters therefore doe heere againe profeſſe to all the world, that they no further deſire the overthrowe of the Prelats, then they ſhall proue that their ſtanding is dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory both to Chriſt &amp; to the King; and that they take
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21472:24"/>nothing from the Prelats, but what they giue to Chriſt, his Church, the King, &amp; the Civill Magiſtrats vnder him: the Prelats unjuſtly keeping that from them, which by the word of God is their due, and which the ſaid Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are readie to yeeld unto them, before they deſire to ſee the overthrow of the Prelats: who (we doubt not) will appeare to be enemyes (though in a myſterie) to God, to the King, and to his people, even in their very Callings and Offices.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="opposition">
                  <head>10. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shall we hearken to the Offer of ſuch as are not yet agreed amongſt themſelues what they would haue? There are not two of them of one minde: and therefore it is to no purpoſe to hearken unto them. Let them firſt agree amongſt themſelues, and tell us what they would haue, and then they ſhall be heard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 They are all agreed alreadie vpon theſe poynts: that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the Ceremonies are ſcandalous, and ought, by thoſe that are in authoritie, to be removed; that the Eccleſiaſticall Government of other reformed Churches is more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the word of God, then the Government by Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan Prelates; that Pluraliſts, Nonreſidents, and dumbe Miniſters ought not to be tolerated in any Chriſtian Church; that it is fitter we ſhould conforme our ſelues to other Reformed Churches in our Liturgie, Ceremonies, &amp; Diſcipline, then to the accurſed Synagogue of Rome. Their differences are onely about the maner of maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe pointes. Let them hearken to the Miniſters
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21472:25"/>in the things wherin they all are alreadie agreed, and they will not trouble them with any diſagreements: Yea, they ſhall finde, that in their differences they will agree better <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> then they would haue them.</item>
                     <item>2. If they diſagree ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, as the Prelats would beare men in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, they haue the leſſe cauſe to feare them, &amp; may with more hope of prevailing enter into this Tryall with them. But the truth is, that their differences are neither halfe ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, nor halfe ſo great, as thoſe that be among the Prelats.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="opposition">
                  <head>11. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Either their Propoſitions are falſe, and ſufficiently confuted by their owne practiſe; or if they be true, then why doe they ioynt to our Church, which is gouerned by the Prelates? why doe they deſire to execute a publike Miniſtery under them? why doe they not wholly with the Browniſts ſeparate, and get them to Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam to their holy brethren there.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                        <hi>1.</hi> The practiſe of the Miniſters herein is no way contrary to their Propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: &amp; this is a moſt deſperate ſhift in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Prelats, to preſſ the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> herewith.</item>
                     <item>2. They proteſt (to the ſha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of the Prelats, &amp; to the testifying of their charitable loue to thoſe of the Miniſterie, which are otherwiſe minded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themſelues) that they are perſwaded, that many of the Conforming Miniſters are (notwithſtanding the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and corruptions in their calling and ſtanding) true Miniſters of Ieſus Chriſt, and indued with gifts from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for that holy functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; And that the Churches which they teach (howſoever in their Conſtitution very defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21472:25"/>and unperfect) are true Churches; whoſe willing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting themſelues unto their Miniſterie maketh the very outward calling it ſelfe of the ſaid Miniſters to be ſuch as it is. And therefore ſo long as (their conſciences being in the meane time vnconvinced of theſe their errors where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d) God taketh not away their Miniſteriall gifts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, and ſo long as their Churches cleaue unto them (though in their entrance &amp; continuance they were, and are guiltie of much ſinne, in approving by Conformitie and Subſcription the Iurisdiction of Prelats) they thinke it not juſt wholly to ſeparate from them and their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, but are content, though with ſome griefe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſo far forth to joyne with them in the worſhip of God, as they can without their perſonall Communion with them in thoſe corruptions, which in their weaknes they yeeld vnto.</item>
                     <item>3. If the Prelats ſhall ſtill hold the things <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in queſtion in ſuch ſort as of late they haue done, &amp; ſhall vrge them ſo hotely as they begin; both the Miniſters &amp; many of the people wilbe forced to leaue their ordinary ſtanding in theſe Churches. In which regard they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray that they may be exempted from the Prelats, &amp; may haue liberty granted vnto them by the King, to ſerue God according to his owne will revealed in his word, without any Humane Traditions. As for that publique Miniſterie derived from the Prelats, beſides that it cannot be entered into without yeelding to corruption &amp; ſinne, it is alſo very defectiue, &amp;, to ſpeake the truth, little more then a halfe Miniſterie, if it be compared with the Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Office commanded and commended vnto vs by the Holy Ghoſt. Which the Miniſters diſcerning, and percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving plainly that there is litle or no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to be had in the exerciſing of ſuch a Miniſterie, as hitherto they haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21472:26"/>they are bold to make their humble Suite to his Maieſtie, that they may be freed from the Prelats vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion over them, and may be vnder the guidance &amp; Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Civill Magiſtrats; unles by ſuch an indifferent Tryall as is heere Offered, the Prelats ſhall iuſtify their Callings and Courſes to be of God.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="opposition">
                  <head>12. OPPOSITION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A vaine thing it is to yeeld to any ſuch Offer. For who muſt iudge on which ſide the truth is. They name none; And when they haue been heard to oppoſe and Anſwer what they can, they will not ſtand to any mans definitiue ſentence, but will continue obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſtill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>ANSWER.</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. In deſiring that the whole cariage of this intended Conference may be publiſhed, they make all the world to be Iudges thereof; even the Prelats and the Papiſts them ſelues, &amp; all that ſhall read the ſame.</item>
                     <item>2. They do not think <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it lawfull in any matter of Religion, much leſſe in matters of ſo great conſequence, to ſettle their conſciences vpon the definitiue ſentence of any perſon abſolutely: that is, ſo far as to renounce any thing which they haue believed, becauſe ſuch or ſuch iudge it to be otherwiſe. For ſo they might both headily &amp; wilfully betray the truth of Chriſt, and inthrall themſelues to error, and alſo detract from Chriſt and his bleſſed word their proper right, and giue it unto men. It ſhould therefore content any Chriſtianly affected man, that the Miniſters are content to offer their Defence of theſe poynts to the view of all, to skan and to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21472:26"/>weigh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo far forth to judge therof, as (if their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do not ſatisfie them) to giue them leaue to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne them of error: which wilbe a Iudgment heavie enough to them, if notwithſtanding they ſhall ſtill perſiſt in their former opinions.</item>
                     <item>3. It may pleaſe God, that by the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and force of thoſe Arguments or Anſwers that ſhal <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> be propounded, both ſides may thinke themſelues ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and one ſide yeeld. If the Prelates haue this grace to yeeld, then his Majeſty &amp; the State know beſt what they haue to doe in ſuch a Caſe. If the Miniſters yeeld, then the greateſt matter that can be expected of them, is Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Conformity: which if they ſhall refuſe, the Law is open; ſo that in this caſe there needes no Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſentence of a Iudge. It both ſides reſt vnſatisfied, and continew perſwaded ſtill, that the truth is on their ſide, it were impious for either ſide in ſuch a caſe to commit the abſolute determination therof vnto the will and pleaſure of any man or men whomſoeuer. And it were vniuſt for either ſide, to require Iudges either incompetent, or not indifferent. For as the Prelats might iuſtly (except they would wilfully betray their owne cauſe) refuſe ſuch to be Iudges, as haue in any degree inclined more to the Minis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters then to them; ſo may the Miniſters in like maner as iuſtly refuſe to ſtand to the Iudgment and determination of ſuch, as incline more to the Prelats then to them; much more of ſuch, as haue ſhewed themſelues maine patrons and vpholders of the Prelats, and adverſaries to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. Sith therfore the Prelats can not ſet forth any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or perſons, to whom it is meet to commit the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute determination of ſo great a cauſe, it were very vniuſt, and vnequall, to binde the Miniſters to ſtand to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe that are partiall.</item>
                     <item>4. It is needles to name <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21472:27"/>Iudges: his Maieſtie, the Civill Magiſtrats vnder him, and the High Court of Parliament (though the Miniſters ſhould appeale from them) would in this caſe judge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and their Cauſe, yea and are bound ſoe to doe. Whoſe Iudgment if it goe againſt the Miniſters, and it appeare to be righteous; the more they ſhall neglect the ſame, and refuſe to ſubmit themſelues vnto it, the more groſſe &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary they ſhall ſhew themſelues to be: and with the more honor and credit may the State ioyne with the Prelats, in making and executing Lawes for the ſuppresſing of them, and their Errors; which is as much advantage as any Chriſtian can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre over any Enemies of the truth. And what would the Prelats haue more?</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 19.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Many deviſes are in a mans heart; but the Counſell of the Lord shall ſtand.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Math: 22:21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Giue unto Caeſar the thinges which are Caeſars; and giue unto God thoſe things which are Gods.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:21472:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
